Now that we've seen how to access individual numbers in a two dimensional array,
我们已经知道怎么在二维数组里访问单个值了
say we wanted to do more than that,
假如我们想进一步操作
like calculate the average grades that all the students have achieved in English.
比如计算所有学生的英语平均分
This means we need to go through each and every student's grade in a particular row.
这就意味着我们需要访问相应行中每个学生的分数
Remember that a two dimensional array is basically an array of arrays.
记住 二维数组本质上就是数组的数组
So, each row here is an array by itself.
因此 这里的每一行本身就是一个数组
So, if we wanted to access every single item in a particular row,
所以 如果我们想访问某一行的每一项
we specify the first number to be the index of that array.
我们就需要指定第一个数字为该数组的索引
But the second index, however,
至于第二个索引
we don't want a specific item,
因为我们不想要某个项
we want all of them.
而想要全部项
So we can surround this with a loop that uses i as
所以我们可以把这整个用循环括起来 用 i 作为计数器
a counter which starts from zero and as long as i is less than five.
从 0 开始计数 直到 i 不再小于 5
And then we can actually use this loop counter as our index here.
然后我们可以用这个循环计数器作这里的索引
Now, this loop counter i would have all the values from zero to
于是 这个循环计数器 i 就会包含所有的值 从 0 到 5
five while one is specifically for the English row,
而这个 1 则指明是英语那一行
which means once we run this loop we're accessing every student in the English row.
也就意味着 一旦我们执行这个循环 我们就能访问英语行中的每个学生
So our loop would go through every item in this particular row.
也就是我们的循环会访问这一行的每一项
Let's see how we could use this to calculate the average in a Java function.
现在来看看我们可以怎么应用这个 在 Java 函数里计算平均分
English average is a function that calculates the average of a two dimensional array.
englishAverage 这个函数能计算一个二维数组的平均值
It takes in this two dimensional array of integers as an input parameter and returns
该函数以这个二维整数数组作为输入参数
a double value which is equal to the average
返回一个双精度值
of all the items in that two dimensional array.
而该值就等于这个二维数组里所有项的平均值
This loop here is the one that we've just created earlier.
这个循环是我们之前创建的
It starts with a loop counter i equals
一开始是循环计数器 i 等于 0
zero and keeps going as long as i is less than five.
会一直执行直到 i 不再小于 5
And inside, we're accessing the grades of one and i.
在这里面 我们要访问 grades [1] [i]
Remember that grades of one and i access every single student in the row of English.
记住 grades [1] [i] 会访问英语行中的每个学生
So this loop here would go through all the students in the English array.
所以这个循环会访问英语数组中的所有学生
Now what we want to do is add up all these values inside this English array.
现在我们要把英语数组里的所有值都加起来
So we can do that by declaring a total variable at the top
因此我们要在上面声明一个变量 即 total
and add this value to this total variable every single time in the loop.
然后每次循环都把这个值和变量 total 加起来
By the end of this loop,
这样等循环结束
total would have the sum of all the values and grades and then we can start
total 就会得到 grades 里所有值的总和
calculating the average by dividing that with the number of items in the array.
而我们就可以开始计算平均值了 也就是让总和除以数组项数
Once we've calculated average,
等我们算好平均值
we could safely return it as the result of the function.
就可以安全地将其返回出来 作为函数的结果
Notice that I've divided this by five point zero not just five,
注意我是把这个除以 5.0 而不仅是 5
because total was declared as an integer.
因为 total 声明为一个整数
And I want the result of the division to become a double. That's perfect.
而我想让除法运算的结果变为双精度值 完美
Now let's see what we need to do if we wanted to calculate the average of a column,
现在来看看 如果想计算一列的平均值 我们得怎么做
like finding the average grade for Sandra, for example.
以算出 Sandra 的平均成绩为例
To calculate the average grade for Sandra means we need to
要计算 Sandra 的平均成绩
go through every item in a particular column.
我们需要访问一列里的每一项
This should be very similar to what we've done with the English average,
这和我们计算英语平均分是很相似的
except that now we want to go through every subject array, not just the one.
除了一点 那就是我们得访问每个科目数组 而不仅仅是一个
Which means our first index here has to be the loop counter i while
这也就意味着 这里的第一个索引应为循环计数器 i
the second number here would be equal to the index of the person who we're interested in.
而第二个数字则应等于我们感兴趣的那个人的索引号
In the case of Sandra, that would become two.
对于 Sandra 来说 该值为 2
Now this means that this loop would go through
这就意味着这个循环
all the grades that Sandra has achieved in all the subjects.
会访问 Sandra 各科的成绩
Let's see how we could use that in some java code.
我们来看看如何在 Java 代码里使用这个
The function Sandra average takes in a two dimensional array as
函数 sandraAverage 以一个二维数组为输入参数
an input and calculates the average and returns it as a double.
会进行平均值计算并将该值以双精度的类型返回出来
It starts by declaring this total variable and initializing to
首先 声明变量 total 并将其初始化为 0
zero and then it loops over all the grades under the Sandra column.
然后对 Sandra 一列的所有成绩进行循环操作
This is done by using the loop counter i as
这个操作需要以循环计数器 i 作为第一个索引
the first index and the number two for Sandra as a second index.
而 Sandra 一列的编号 2 则为第二个索引
And again, inside the loop we're just adding grades to our total every single time.
还是一样 在循环里 我们每次都会将 grades 与 total 相加
So by the end of this loop we could just divide our total value by four which is
这样等到循环结束 我们就可以让 total 除以 4
the number of subjects to get the average grades
也就是除以科目数
that Sandra has achieved and then we can return that.
从而得到 Sandra 的平均成绩 并将其返回出来
That looks pretty good. However, there are a few things that we can change in
看起来很不错 不过 我们还可以修改一下这个函数
this function to make it more readable and easier to understand.
使其可读性更强 更容易理解
First of all, these numbers four and two and four point zero don't really mean
首先 对于没看过这个数组的人来说
much to someone who hasn't seen the array
这些数字 4、2 和 4.0 意义不明
before especially if they don't know what the array has inside it.
如果他们不知道数组里有什么 那就更是如此了
So to make the function more generic we can actually
所以要让函数更通俗易懂
figure out those numbers inside the code itself,
我们可以让代码体现出这些数字的含义
like four which is equal to the number of subjects
比如 让代表科目数的 4
can be deduced from the two dimensional array that's passed in as a parameter.
从这个作为参数的二维数组上推断出来
We can do that in the very first line of our function by using the keyword length again.
要实现这一点 我们可以在函数第一行再次使用关键字 length
Remember that when we use the length keyword,
记住 当我们使用关键字 length 的时候
we're counting the number of elements or items in that array.
我们计算的是数组里的元素或项数
And since grades is an array of arrays,
由于 grades 是个数组的数组
grades.length tells us how many arrays there
grades.length 会告诉我们这个二维数组里有多少个数组
are in this two dimensional array which is equal to the number of subjects.
而数组数又等于科目数
So we can store that in a variable called subjects and
因此我们可以将得出的值赋给变量  subjects
now replace any four with that variable instead.
从而将所有 4 都替换成这个变量
And when we get to the four point zero down here,
来到这里的 4.0
because we want to make sure that our subjects is a double,
因为我们想确保 subjects 是个双精度数
even though it's declared as an integer,
哪怕它被声明为整数
we can cast it to a double row like we have learned before.
所以我们可以将它转换为一个双精度数 就像我们之前学到的那样
So the average is now calculated by dividing
于是现在要计算平均数
total with the number of subjects but cast it into a double.
就是用 total 除以 subjects 的值 不过该值被转换为一个双精度值
This looks much better now because this would work for any two dimensional array,
现在看起来好多了 任何二维数组都能应用这个函数了
no matter how many subjects are inside it.
无论数组里有多少科目都不怕
One last thing we can do here is to generalize this
我们可以做的最后一个操作 是把这个 2 泛化
too instead of having a function specifically for Sandra.
这样函数就不是特地针对 Sandra 而设的了
And instead of having a function that calculates
而是可以为我们指定的任意学生
the average for any student that we specify.
计算平均值
The best way to do that is to have a generic function called,
最好的泛化办法是创建一个泛型函数
studentAverage that now has an extra input parameter which is an integer student.
我们管它叫 studentAverage 该函数现在多了个输入参数 即 int student
So it takes in the actual two dimensional array with all the grades in
所以该函数接受两个参数 一个是包含所有成绩的二维数组
it and the student index whom we're interested in calculating the average for.
另一个是 student 这能索引出我们想计算平均值的那名学生
So inside, we could just replace the square brackets here with this variable student
而在这里面 我们可以把这里的方括号替换为变量 student
which means whatever number we pass in as
这也就意味着 无论我们输入什么数字作为参数
an input parameter would be used to access this grade's two dimensional array.
都会用于访问这个二维数组 grades
Now our studentAverage function would work for any student we
现在我们的 studentAverage 函数既可对我们指定的任意学生进行操作
specify and with any two dimensional array that has any number of subjects in it.
也可对具备任意科目数的任意二维数组进行操作
So what if we wanted to do more analysis on this two dimensional array?
那如果我们想对这个二维数组进行更多的分析操作呢？
Say we needed to loop over the entire array,
假设我们需要对整个数组进行循环操作
accessing every single number in it.
访问里面的每个值
It almost seems like we need a loop for every row and
似乎我们得分别为每行建一个循环
inside that loop we need to go through every item in that row.
而在每个循环里 我们还需要访问该行的每一项
A loop of loops?
循环里的循环？
Yep, that's actually possible.
是的 这是可能的
Just like nested ifs.
就像 if 嵌套
We can actually have nested loops as well. Let's see how.
我们也可以有循环嵌套 我们来看看要怎样操作